<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-10-20T09:19:35-04:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Wegley Kelly Lab</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Linda Wegley Kelly</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Wegley Kelly lab grows!</title><link href="/New-members2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Wegley Kelly lab grows!" /><published>2021-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/New-members2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="/New-members2021/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-wegley-kelly-lab-is-joined-by-four-new-students&quot;&gt;The Wegley Kelly Lab is joined by four new students!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;graduate-students-catherine-mullenmeister-emily-nixon-and-sabrina-sauri&quot;&gt;Graduate students: Catherine Mullenmeister, Emily Nixon, and Sabrina Sauri&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;post-bac-intern-bibi-rensson&quot;&gt;Post-bac intern: Bibi Rensson&lt;/h2&gt;</content><author><name>Linda Wegley Kelly</name></author><category term="New members" /><summary type="html">The Wegley Kelly Lab is joined by four new students! Graduate students: Catherine Mullenmeister, Emily Nixon, and Sabrina Sauri Post-bac intern: Bibi Rensson</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Zach was published in Frontiers in Marine Science!</title><link href="/publication-Frontiers-in-Marine-Science/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Zach was published in Frontiers in Marine Science!" /><published>2021-04-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-04-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/publication-Frontiers-in-Marine-Science</id><content type="html" xml:base="/publication-Frontiers-in-Marine-Science/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;three-dimensional-molecular-cartography-of-the-caribbean-reef-building-coral-orbicella-faveolata&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.3389/fmars.2021.627724&quot;&gt;Three-Dimensional Molecular Cartography of the Caribbean Reef-Building Coral Orbicella faveolata&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;mark-little1-emma-e-george-milou-g-i-arts-jade-shivak-sean-benlerjoel-huckeba-zachary-a-quinlan-vittorio-boscaro-benjamin-muellerana-georgina-cobián-güemes10-maria-isabel-rojas-brandie-white-daniel-petrascynthia-b-silveira-andreas-f-haas-linda-wegley-kelly-mark-j-a-vermeijrobert-a-quinn-patrick-j-keeling-pieter-c-dorrestein-forest-rohwer-and-ty-n-f-roach&quot;&gt;Mark Little1, Emma E. George, Milou G. I. Arts, Jade Shivak, Sean Benler,Joel Huckeba, Zachary A. Quinlan, Vittorio Boscaro, Benjamin Mueller,Ana Georgina Cobián Güemes10, Maria Isabel Rojas, Brandie White, Daniel Petras,Cynthia B. Silveira, Andreas F. Haas, Linda Wegley Kelly, Mark J. A. Vermeij,Robert A. Quinn, Patrick J. Keeling, Pieter C. Dorrestein, Forest Rohwer and Ty N. F. Roach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All organisms host a diversity of associated viruses, bacteria, and protists, collectively defined as the holobiont. While scientific advancements have enhanced the understanding of the functional roles played by various components of the holobiont, there is a growing need to integrate multiple types of molecular data into spatially and temporally resolved frameworks. To that end, we mapped 16S and 18S rDNA metabarcoding, metatranscriptomics, and metabolomic data onto three-dimensional reconstructions of coral colonies to examine microbial diversity, microbial gene expression, and biochemistry on two colonies of the ecologically important, reef-building coral, Orbicella faveolata and their competitors (i.e., adjacent organisms interacting with the corals: fleshy algae, turf algae, hydrozoans, and other corals). Overall, no statistically significant spatial patterns were observed among the samples for any of the data types; instead, strong signatures of the macroorganismal hosts (e.g., coral, algae, hydrozoa) were detected, in the microbiome, the transcriptome, and the metabolome. The 16S rDNA analysis demonstrated higher abundance of Firmicutes in the coral microbiome than in its competitors. A single bacterial amplicon sequence variant from the genus Clostridium was found exclusively in all O. faveolata samples. In contrast to microbial taxa, a portion of the functionally annotated bacterial RNA transcripts (6.86%) and metabolites (1.95%) were ubiquitous in all coral and competitor samples. Machine learning analysis of microbial transcripts revealed elevated T7-like cyanophage-encoded photosystem II transcripts in O. faveolata samples, while sequences involved in bacterial cell division were elevated in turf algal and interface samples. Similar analysis of metabolites revealed that bacterial-produced antimicrobial and antifungal compounds were highly enriched in coral samples. This study provides insight into the spatial and biological patterning of the coral microbiome, transcriptome, and metabolome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Linda Wegley Kelly</name></author><category term="publication" /><summary type="html">Three-Dimensional Molecular Cartography of the Caribbean Reef-Building Coral Orbicella faveolata Mark Little1, Emma E. George, Milou G. I. Arts, Jade Shivak, Sean Benler,Joel Huckeba, Zachary A. Quinlan, Vittorio Boscaro, Benjamin Mueller,Ana Georgina Cobián Güemes10, Maria Isabel Rojas, Brandie White, Daniel Petras,Cynthia B. Silveira, Andreas F. Haas, Linda Wegley Kelly, Mark J. A. Vermeij,Robert A. Quinn, Patrick J. Keeling, Pieter C. Dorrestein, Forest Rohwer and Ty N. F. Roach</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Zach was published in Functional Ecology!</title><link href="/publication-functional-ecology/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Zach was published in Functional Ecology!" /><published>2021-02-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-02-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/publication-functional-ecology</id><content type="html" xml:base="/publication-functional-ecology/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;differential-resistance-and-acclimation-of-two-coral-species-to-chronic-nutrient-enrichment-reflect-life-history-traits&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2435.13780&quot;&gt;Differential resistance and acclimation of two coral species to chronic nutrient enrichment reflect life history traits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;michael-d-fox-craig-e-nelson--thomas-a-oliver--zachary-a-quinlan--kristina-remple--jess-glanz--jennifer-e-smith--hollie-m-putnam&quot;&gt;Michael D. Fox, Craig E. Nelson,  Thomas A. Oliver,  Zachary A. Quinlan,  Kristina Remple,  Jess Glanz,  Jennifer E. Smith,  Hollie M. Putnam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The effects of nutrient pollution on coral reef ecosystems are multifaceted. Numerous experiments have sought to identify the physiological effects of nutrient enrichment on reef‐building corals, but the results have been variable and sensitive to choices of nutrient quantity, chemical composition and exposure duration.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To test the effects of chronic, ecologically relevant nutrient enrichment on coral growth and photophysiology, we conducted a 5‐week continuous dosing experiment on two Hawaiian coral species, Porites compressa and Pocillopora acuta. We acclimated coral fragments to five nutrient concentrations (0.1–7 µM urn:x-wiley:02698463:media:fec13780:fec13780-math-0001 and 0.06–2.24 µM urn:x-wiley:02698463:media:fec13780:fec13780-math-0002) with constant stoichiometry 2.5:1 nitrate to phosphate) bracketing in situ observations from reefs throughout the Pacific.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nutrient enrichment linearly increased photophysiological performance of both species within 3 weeks. The effect of nutrients on P. acuta photochemical efficiency increased through time while a consistent response in P. compressa indicated acclimation to elevated nutrients within 5 weeks. Endosymbiont densities and total chlorophyll concentrations also increased proportionally with nutrient enrichment in P. acuta, but not in P. compressa, revealing contrasting patterns of host–symbiont acclimatization.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The two species also exhibited contrasting effects of nutrient enrichment on skeletal growth. Calcification was enhanced at low nutrient enrichment (1 µM urn:x-wiley:02698463:media:fec13780:fec13780-math-0003) in P. acuta, but comparable to the control at higher concentrations, whereas calcification was reduced in P. compressa (30%–35%) above 3 µM urn:x-wiley:02698463:media:fec13780:fec13780-math-0004.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stable isotope analysis revealed species‐specific nitrogen uptake dynamics in the coral–algal symbiosis. The endosymbionts of P. acuta exhibited increased nitrogen uptake (decreased δ15N) and incorporation (19%–31% decrease in C:N ratios) across treatments. In contrast, P. compressa endosymbionts maintained constant δ15N values and low levels of nitrogen incorporation (9%–11% decrease in C:N ratios). The inability of P. acuta to regulate endosymbiont nutrient uptake may indicate an emerging destabilization in the coral–algal symbiosis under nutrient enrichment that could compromise resistance to additional environmental stressors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our results highlight species‐specific differences in the coral–algal symbiosis, which influence responses to chronic nutrient enrichment. These findings showcase how symbioses can vary among closely related taxa and underscore the importance of considering how life‐history traits modify species response to environmental change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Linda Wegley Kelly</name></author><category term="publication" /><summary type="html">Differential resistance and acclimation of two coral species to chronic nutrient enrichment reflect life history traits Michael D. Fox, Craig E. Nelson, Thomas A. Oliver, Zachary A. Quinlan, Kristina Remple, Jess Glanz, Jennifer E. Smith, Hollie M. Putnam</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Wegley Kelly Lab join Scripps Institution of Oceanography!</title><link href="/Joining-SIO/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Wegley Kelly Lab join Scripps Institution of Oceanography!" /><published>2021-01-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-01-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/Joining-SIO</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Joining-SIO/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-wegley-kelly-lab-is-joining-sio&quot;&gt;The Wegley Kelly lab is joining SIO!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We are extremely excited to being joining the Scripps marine biology program! Our lab specializes in multi-omic analyses to understand coral reef dynamics and we are extatic to both continue our collaborations at SIO and also form many new ones.
 &lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;br /&gt;
We cannot wait to meet our new colleagues!
-From Linda and Zach&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Linda Wegley Kelly</name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html">The Wegley Kelly lab is joining SIO! We are extremely excited to being joining the Scripps marine biology program! Our lab specializes in multi-omic analyses to understand coral reef dynamics and we are extatic to both continue our collaborations at SIO and also form many new ones. We cannot wait to meet our new colleagues! -From Linda and Zach</summary></entry></feed>